Guide to the Robert Marsham- Townshend Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robert Marsham-Townshend papers
1853-1910
GEN MSS 482
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.67
(4 boxes)
Letters and diaries belonging to Robert Marsham-Townshend containing descriptions of his travels around the world. Many of the letters are written to him, though there is a group of 22 letters written by him to a relative named Harriet, dated 1856-1864. Correspondents include Henry Alabaster, interpreter to the King in Siam; scientists W. S. Atkinson and Robert Stirling; George Ferguson Bowen, first governor of Queensland, Australia; in addition to numerous family members and other acquaintances. Stirling writes at length from the Sandwich Islands describing earthquakes and volcanic eruptions, a particular interest of Marsham-Townshend's. There are also fifteen letters from Youhannah El Karey, a missionary from Nablous, near Jaffa, Palestine. The 18 diaries span the dates 1853-1876, and carry descriptions of travel to Brazil, Egypt, Hong Kong, the Philippines, China, Japan, Argentina, Peru, Bolivia, Chile, Panama, El Salvador, Honduras, California, Australia, Indonesia, Siam, India, Persia, the Middle East, South Africa, Russia, and Europe. There is a great deal of geographic and volcanic observation, as well as descriptions of cities, cultures, and peoples encountered. Accompanied by a bound notebook with notes on volcanoes throughout the world, two passports for Marsham-Townshend to use in Persia, and three contracts and receipts for hiring mules and drivers in Persia.
Marsham-Townshend, Robert, 1834-1914
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Charles Apfelbaum on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
ROBERT MARSHAM-TOWNSHEND (1834-1914)
Robert Marsham, later Robert Marsham-Townshend, British world traveller, was the second son of Charles Marsham, 2nd Earl of Romney. He was a fellow of the Royal Geographic Society, worked in the Diplomatic Service from 1855 to 1859, and served as Lieutenant in the Kent Militia Artillery from 1859 to 1869. Marsham married Clara Catherine Paley in 1877.
Scope and Contents
The Robert Marsham-Townshend Papers consist of letters and diaries containing descriptions of Robert Marsham-Townshend's travels around the world. The collection is arranged into three series: Correspondence, Diaries, and Other Papers, and spans the dates 1853-1910.
Many of the letters are written to him, though there is a group of 22 letters written by him to a relative identified only as Harriet, dated 1856-1864. Correspondents include Henry Alabaster, interpreter to the King in Siam; scientists W. S. Atkinson and Robert Stirling; George Ferguson Bowen, first governor of Queensland, Australia; in addition to numerous family members and other acquaintances. Stirling writes at length from the Sandwich Islands describing earthquakes and volcanic eruptions, a particular interest of Marsham-Townshend's. There are also fifteen letters from Youhannah El Karey, a missionary from Nablous, near Jaffa, Palestine.
The 18 diaries span the dates 1853-1876, and carry descriptions of travel to Brazil, Egypt, Hong Kong, the Philippines, China, Japan, Argentina, Peru, Bolivia, Chile, Panama, El Salvador, Honduras, California, Australia, Indonesia, Siam (Thailand), India, Persia (Iran), the Mideast, South Africa, Russia, and Europe. There is a great deal of geographic and volcanic observation, as well as descriptions of cities, cultures, and peoples encountered.
The papers are accompanied by a bound notebook with notes on volcanoes throughout the world, two passports for Marsham-Townshend to use in Persia, and three contracts and receipts for hiring mules and drivers in Persia.
Volcanoes; Voyages and travels; Asia -- Description and travel; Australia -- Description and travel; Central America -- Description and travel; Earthquakes -- Hawaii; Europe -- Description and travel; Middle East -- Description and travel; South Africa -- Description and travel; South America -- Description and travel; Diaries; Alabaster, Henry, -1884; Atkinson, W. S. (William Stephen), 1820-1876; Bowen, George Ferguson, 1821-1899; El Karey, Youhannah; Marsham-Townshend, Robert, 1834-1914; Stirling, Robert
- Correspondence, 1856-1910; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into Outgoing and Incoming correspondence, and is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - OUTGOING
    - Marsham, Margaret, 1861 Oct 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - [----?], Harriet, 1856-64 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - INCOMING
    - "A-C" general, 1866-68 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Alabaster, Henry, 1868 Jan 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Atkinson, W. S. (William Stephen), 1867 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bowen, George Ferguson, 1866 Dec 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cayley, Henry, 1867 Aug-Nov (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "D-H" general, 1867-1910, n.y. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      For a letter by C. Hunt dated 1868 Mar 4, see: Marsham, Margaret, folder 16
    - El Karey, Youhannah
      - Correspondence, 1882-84 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, 1897-99 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Canceled check, carte-de-visite photographs, flower cards, and empty envelopes, 1899, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "I-M" general, 1867-68 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Letter from Anne Marsham dated 1868 Jul 11 encloses a letter from Charles Marsham, Earl of Romney
    - Jennings, P. H., 1886 May (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Knox, Thomas George, 1867 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Marsham, Margaret, 1868 Jul 11 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Encloses a letter from C. Hunt, dated 1868 Mar 4
    - Pelly, Lewis, 1868 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "R-S" general, 1867-68 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      For a letter by Charles Marsham, Earl of Romney dated Jul 11 1868, see: Anne Marsham, folder 13
    - Shaw, Madan, 1868 Jan-Jul (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Stirling, Robert, 1867-68 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - "T-W" general, 1856-99 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Diaries, 1853-1876; Series II; 0.31; (2.5 boxes)
  Series II, Diaries, contains diaries listed in chronological order.
  - June 17 - August 13 1853 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Paris, Switzerland, Germany, Belgium, Italy
  - March 7 - Sept. 17 1856 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Voyage to Brazil, and his stay there
  - Directions. Sept. 21 - Nov. 4 1857 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    List of addresses in the front, travel journal kept while traveling in Brazil in back
  - Tocantins excursion 1858 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Travel to Tocantins River, Brazil October 5 - December 18. Back of book includes drafts of letters dated October 1858 - March 1859
  - April 17 - August 4 1861 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    France, Egypt, Singapore, Hong Kong, Canton
  - August 5th 1861 to April 3d 1862, 1861-62 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Japan, China, Singapore, Sri Lanka
  - July 8 - Decr. 31 1862 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Portugal to Brazil and Argentina. List of mail either sent or received at different ports between 1862 and 1868 in front
  - Jany. 1 - June 28 1863 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Argentina, Chile, Bolivia, Peru
  - "Ascent of the Volcano of Arequipa etc. etc. 1863" (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Diary of two ascents, June 10 and 17 1863, with notes on previous ascents in front of volume in Spanish and English
  - June 29th 1863 to March 4th 1864, 1863-64 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Peru, Panama, California, Panama, Guatemala, El Salvador, Honduras
  - July 6th 1865 to June 9th 1866, 1865-66 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Australia, New Zealand
  - June 9 - Novr. 29 1866 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Indonesia, Philippines, Siam
  - Novr. 29th 1866 to Feby. 21st 1868, 1866-68 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Siam, India. Folded sheet of paper carrying handwritten journal from July 16 to July 27 laid in loose
  - Feby. 21 - July 23 1868 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    India, Persia, Arabian Peninsula, Russia, Germany
  - June 17 - Sept. 23 1871 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    Gibraltar, Spain, Portugal, France
  - March 12 - July 3 1872 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    France, Italy
  - March 22 - July 18, 1873 and June 1 - December 11, 1876, 1873, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 37a)
    1873: France, Mideast, Italy, Austria, Germany. 1876: Mideast, Reunion, Mauritius, Madagascar, South Africa
  - Sept. 3, 1875 to Jan. 3, 1876, 1875-76 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    Eastern Europe, Italy, Corfu, Majorca, Algeria
- Other Papers, 1868, n.d.; Series III; 0.11; (.5 box)
  Series III, Other Papers, contains miscellaneous other writings, documents, and financial papers.
  - Volcanoes &c. Bound volume (Box 4, Folder 39)
    Notes on volcanoes around the world, with mathematical tables, a sketch of a volcano
  - Passports in Persian Language, [1868] (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Contracts and receipts, 1868 Apr-Jun (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Notes on sizes of buildings, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 42)